Cole, David L. Papers 5588
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
David L. Cole Papers
1940-1975
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Cole, David L.
5588
117.5 cubic feet
117.5 linear ft.
Records (documents), case files.
Correspondence, reports, minutes, and related materials.
3337258
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
AR, CE, CB, June 05, 2013
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, June 05, 2019
Biographical / Historical
David Lawrence Cole was a graduate of Harvard University (BS., 1921) and Fairleigh Dickinson University (LL.B., 1924, LL.D., 1964.) Although he practiced law in Paterson, N.J. from 1926 until his death as senior partner in the law firm of Cole, Berman & Belksy, David Cole will chiefly be remembered for a distinguished career as a government arbitrator and mediator. In this field he served on numerous state and federal boards and in various governmental agencies. Cole was chairman of the New Jersey State Board of Mediation; a public member of Region 2, United States War Labor Board; and chairman of the Presidential Boards of Inquiry in the bituminous coal industry (1948) and in the longshore industry (1953, 1968). Cole was also a member or chairman of numerous Presidential Emergency Boards which settled disputes in the railroad and airline industries (1948-1958); the chairman of the conciliation service for the New York City transit service (1961-1965); director of the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service (1952-1953); chairman of the New Jersey Governor's Committee on Public Utility Strike Service (1952-1953); member of the President's Labor-Management Advisory Committee (1961-1964); and member of the New York Governor's Public Employee Relations Committee (1966-1968), which established the New York State Public Employee Relations Board. Cole was also appointed as chairman of the President's Commission on Industrial Peace in 1973.
Beyond his public service, Mr. Cole was active as a counsel for employer groups in the textile industry (1926-1942) and as an impartial chairman for other labor-management contract disputes. He was also impartial arbitrator for the AFL-CIO Internal Disputes Plan (1954-1976), served as a visiting professor at the New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell University (1954-1955) and was Kestenbaum lecturer at Harvard in 1962. Mr. Cole was the author of INDUSTRIAL PEACE (1963).
Scope and Contents
Includes notes (hand-written and typed), correspondence, reports, minutes, and related materials documenting Cole's career as a government official, lawyer, arbitrator and mediator. Also includes over 750 arbitration awards, decisions, and related documents (arranged, for the most part, alphabetically by name of company) for cases arbitrated by Cole, primarily in the textile, garment, steel, meat-packing, maritime, longshore, farm implement, and transportation industries.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5122: David L. Cole Arbitration Transcripts 5588 AV: David Cole Interviews 5588 mf: David Cole Additional Arbitration Records on Microfilm 5737 OHT: Oral History Interview with David Cole by Jerry N. Hess 6116m: David L. Cole Report on "Conscious Promotion in Practice of Better Labor-Management Cooperation" 6201 OH: Dennis Gaffney Collection of a Paul Cole Interview Audio- Visual Materials 6202: New York State AFL-CIO Paul Cole Files 6202 AV: New York State AFL-CIO Paul Cole Interviews Audio-Visual Materials 6202 OH: New York State AFL-CIO Paul Cole Interviews Oral History on Minidiscs 6202 P(d): New York State AFL-CIO Paul Cole Digital Photographs
Arbitration and award; Absenteeism. Arbitration, Industrial. United States; Arbitration, Industrial. Agricultural machine industry. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Aircraft industry. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Airlines. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Broadcasting. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Clothing industry. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Dairy processing. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Education. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Electric industries. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Electric utilities. New York (N.Y.); Arbitration, Industrial. Entertainment industry. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Firefighters. New York (N.Y.); Arbitration, Industrial. Food industry. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Fur trade. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Law and legislation. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Meat industry. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Merchant marine. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Newspaper publishing. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Public utilities. New Jersey.; Arbitration, Industrial. Publishing. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Railroads. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Retail trade. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Sports industry. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Steel industry. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Stevedores. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Telecommunication. New Jersey.; Arbitration, Industrial. Telecommunication. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Textile industry. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. Transportation. United States.; Arbitration, Industrial. United States. Cases.; Arbitration, Industrial. Women's clothing industry. United States.; Arbitrators, Industrial.; Atomic energy industries. Industrial relations. United States.; Atomic Power. Law and legislation. England.; Bargaining unit. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Bargaining unit. Civil service. United States.; Civil defense and industrial relations. United States.; Coal mining industry. United States. State supervision.; Collective bargaining. Civil service. New York (State).; Collective bargaining. Civil service. United States.; Collective bargaining. Construction industry. United States.; Collective bargaining. Education. New York (State); Collective bargaining. Public utilities. New Jersey.; Collective bargaining. Steel industry. United States.; Collective bargaining. Stevedores. West (U.S.); Collective bargaining. United States. State supervision.; Communism. United States. Public opinion.; Discrimination in employment. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Employee fringe benefits. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Employee fringe benefits. Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. United States.; Employees, Dismissal of. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Employees, Transfer of. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Grievance procedures. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Grievance procedures. Civil service. New York (State); Grievance procedures. Petroleum industry. United States.; Grievance procedures. United States. State supervision.; Guided missile bases. Industrial relations. United States.; Hospitals. Industrial relations. New York (State).; Hours of labor. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Hours of labor. Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. United States.; Industrial relations. United States. State supervision.; Industrial safety. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Job descriptions. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Job descriptions. Textile industry. United States.; Job security. Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. United States.; Job vacancies. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Labor discipline. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Labor disputes. Air lines. United States.; Labor disputes. Civil service. Law and legislation. United States.; Labor disputes. Civil service. United States.; Labor disputes. Coal mining industry. United States. State supervision.; Labor disputes. Education. New York (State); Labor disputes. Entertainment industry. United States.; Labor disputes. Fire fighters. New York (State); Labor disputes. Law and legislation. United States.; Labor disputes. Merchant marine. United States.; Labor disputes. New Jersey. State supervision.; Labor disputes. Police. New York (State); Labor disputes. Public utilities. New Jersey.; Labor disputes. Steel industry. United States. State supervision.; Labor disputes. Stevedores. United States. State supervision.; Labor disputes. United States. State supervision.; Labor injunction. Coal mining industry. United States.; Labor productivity. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Labor-management cooperation. United States.; Layoffs. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Management rights. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. Air lines. United States.; Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. Civil service. United States.; Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. Laundry industry. New Jersey.; Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. Merchant marine. United States.; Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. Railroads. United States.; Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. Stevedores. United States.; Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. United States. Cases.; Mediation and conciliation. Coal mining industry. United States.; Misconduct. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Nationalization. Coal mining industry. United States.; Newspaper publishing. Technological innovations. United States.; Open and closed shop. Law and legislation. United States.; Open and closed shop. Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. United States.; Open and closed shop. Railroads. United States.; Paid nonwork time. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Pensions. United States. State supervision.; Performance appraisal. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Position classification. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Promotions. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Railroad employees, Minority.; Retirement. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Retirement. Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. United States.; Seniority, Employee. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Steel industry. United States. State supervision.; Stevedores. United States. State supervision.; Strikes and lockouts. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Strikes and lockouts. Civil service. Law and legislation. United States.; Strikes and lockouts. Civil service. New York (State).; Strikes and lockouts. Coal mining industry. United States.; Strikes and lockouts. Law and legislation. United States.; Strikes and lockouts. Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. United States.; Strikes and lockouts. Merchant marine. United States.; Strikes and lockouts. Public utilities. New Jersey.; Strikes and lockouts. Sanitation workers. New York (N.Y.); Strikes and lockouts. Steel industry. United States.; Strikes and lockouts. United States. State supervision.; Trade-union expulsion. United States.; Trade-union merger. United States.; Trade-union security. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Trade-union security. Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. United States.; Trade-unions. Government employees. New York (State); Trade-unions. Government employees. United States.; Trade-unions. Newspaper employees. United States. Jurisdictional disputes.; Trade-unions. Railroads. United States.; Trade-unions. United States. Minority membership.; Unemployment. United States. State supervision.; Wages. Air lines. United States.; Wages. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Wages. Civil service. New York (State); Wages. Civil service. United States.; Wages. Law and legislation. New Jersey.; Wages. Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. United States.; Wages. Merchant marine. United States.; Wages. Minimum wage. Law and legislation. New Jersey.; Wages. Railroads. United States.; Wages. Steel industry. United States.; Wages. Stevedores. United States.; Weekly rest-day. White collar workers.; Work assignments. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Work rules. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Work rules. Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. United States.; Workers' compensation. Civil service. New Jersey. Paterson.; Workers' compensation. United States. State supervision.; Working conditions. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Working conditions. Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. United States.; United States. Economic conditions, 1945-; United States. Economic policy. 1961-; United States. Foreign economic relations.; Anderson, Arvid, 1921-2015; Bechtel, Stephen Davison, 1900-1989; Bernstein, Irving, 1916- 2001; Binion, Russell; Boulware, Lemuel R., 1895-; Brennan, Peter J., 1918-1996; Brennan, William J.; Brownlow, J. A.; Chamberlain, Neil W.; Ching, Cyrus S. (Cyrus Stuart), 1876-1967.; Cole, David L.; Coughlin, Howard,1913-1984; Cox, Archibald, 1912-2004; Crowley, Joseph R.; Dinwoodey, Dean; Doherity, Theresa; Donahue, Charles, 1941-; Donahue, Thomas R., 1928-; Dunlop, John T.(John Thomas), 1914- 2003; Durham, Howard; Edge, Walter E. (Walter Evans), 1873-1956; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969; Feinsinger, Nathan Paul, 1902-1983; Ford, Gerald, 1913-; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965; Garrison, Lloyd; Goldberg, Arthur J.; Gudeman, Edward, 1906-1974; Hall, Paul; Hampton, Robert; Helsby, Robert; Herzog, Paul M., 1906-1986; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968; Kerr, Clark, 1911-2003; Kheel, Theodore Woodrow; Larry, R. Heath; Leiserson, William; Lester, Richard Allen, 1908-; Lieberman, Abraham; Mann, Keith; McDonald, David J. (David John), 1902-1979; McKelvey, Jean T. (Jean Trepp), 1908-1998; Meany, George, 1894-1980; Miller, Marvin Julian, 1914-; Moskow, Michael H.; Neufeld, Maurice F.; Nickerson, John; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994; Nulty, Grace; Perlman, Selig, 1888-1959; Rehmus, Charles; Reuther, Victor G. (Victor George), 1912-2004; Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970; Roberts, Harold Selig, 1911-1970; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979; Scheiber, Israel Ben; Seward, Ralph T. (Ralph Theodore), 1907-; Shultz, George P.; Slichter, Sumner H. (Sumner Huber), 1892-1959; Sprague, Charles; Taft, Philip, 1902-1976; Taylor, George W (George William), 1901-; Travis, H., major; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972; Usery, W. J., c Jr., 1923-; Vatalaro, Ralph; Wallace, Walter; Wirtz, Willard, 1912-2010; Wolff, Sidney; Woodcock, Leonard; AFL-CIO; Airline Stewards and Stewardesses Association; Akron & Barberton Belt Railroad Company; Aloha Airlines, Inc.; Amalgamated Association of Street, Electric Railway and Motor Coach Employees of America; Amalgamated Transit Union; American Airlines; American Arbitration Association; American Arbitration Association. Labor Management Institute; American Communications Association; American Federation of Government Employees; American Federation of Labor; American Federation of Musicians; American Federation of Radio Artists; American Federation of Television and Radio Artists; American Newspaper Guild; Androscoggin Mills (Lewiston, Me.); Atlantic Steamship Company; Babcock & Wilcox Company; Bobbie Brooks, Inc.; Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen; Brotherhood of Railway, Airline, and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express, and Station Employes; Carnegie Steel Company; Civil Service Employees Association (N.Y.); Cleveland Tankers; Communications Workers of America; Defense Plant Corporation; Duplan Corporation; Eastern Air Lines; Flight Engineers' International Association; General Electric Company; Harvard University; Inland Steel Company; International Air Line Pilots Association; International Association of Machinists; Int
3337258
- A, 1944-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  With American Bar Association re soliciting new members and serving on various committees; Irving Abramson, Labor Advisor, Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) Community Services Committee; American Management Association re book review of Cy Ching's Review and Reflection; other routine and personal.
- AFL-CIO - General Correspondence, 1970-1977 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  Includes correspondence with Walter Diehl (International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees and Technicians) re conflict with National Association of Broadcast Employees and Technicians; with Thomas Donahue, Executive Assistant to George Meany discussing various cases and decisions re AFL(American Federation of Labor)-CIO Internal Disputes Plan; includes handwritten notes with George Meany re decisions made by Impartial Umpires and statement by Meany on "Detente"; personal and routine.
- B, 1943-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
  With Wight Bakke; Jules Backman; Solomon Barkin, Textile Workers of America; with William Bristol, Bristol-Myers Co. and Joseph Brophy, Secretary of State of New Jersey re Cole's not being reappointed as Chairman of New Jersey State Mediation Board (1945); other routine and personal.
- C, 1944-1969 (Box 1, Folder 8-11)
  Joseph A. Califano, Jr., Special Assistant to the President, thanking Cole for all his work which helped end the longshoremen dispute (1969); M. P. Catherwood, Dean, New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations (NYSSILR) re Cole speaking at school convocation and his continuing as a visiting professor (1955); Robert B. Chiperfield, U.S. Congressman re government taking over railroads (1952); personal with son Charles, at Harvard, and daughter Elizabeth, at Vassar; Archibald Cox, Professor, Law School, Harvard University and Chairman, National Wage Stabilization Board re report on union-shop issue of non-operating brotherhoods case (1952) and letter congratulating Cox on appointment as chairman of the board; other routine and personal.
- D, 1944-1955 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  With John T. Dunlop, Harvard University and Office of Economic Stabilization re various cases and other personal; routine.
- E, 1945-1955 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Leverett Edwards, Chairman, National Mediation Board re airlines and other cases; letter to President Dwight David Eisenhower from John Eastman, AAA President, recommending Cole's reappointment as Director of the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service; letter from President Eisenhower thanking Cole for his kind sentiments; other routine and personal.
- F, 1944-1958 (Box 2, Folder 4-7)
  I. Robert Feinberg, Arbitrator, re setting up a labor conference; Nathan P. Feinsinger, National War Labor Board (routine and personal) tries to convince Cole to serve on Wage Stabilization Board and discusses Cole's involvement in several cases including work with Harvester; congratulations re Cole's receiving 7th Annual "Brotherhood Award" at National Conference of Christians and Jews; with Jerome Fenton, U.S. Department of Defense, outlining his position and responsibilities in the Department and his involvement with the industrial security program and ideas for improvement, encourages Cole to contact Secretary of Labor James Mitchell re employment; with R. W. Fleming, Director, Industrial Relations Research Association, of which Cole was Legal Counsel, re various Association matters, Cole's teaching at Cornell University; Felix Frankfurter, U.S. Supreme Court re arranging appointment to discuss functions of emergency boards and other routine; other personal and routine..
- G, 1945-1967 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  With Arthur J. Goldberg, U.S. Supreme Court and U.N. Representative (1952-67) re Cole receiving critical fan mail due to a "union-shop report" and re appointment as member of Cole to Missile Sites Labor Commission and personal and routine; with J. W. Greenwood, Jr., Associate Director, FMCS re bringing Cole up to Date on developments in Washington with the FMCS; other routine and personal..
- H, 1944-1965 (Box 3, Folder 5-10)
  Harry B. Haines, Paterson Evening News, re personal, re Cole's work on the steel panel; Harvard University, Paul H. Buck, Dean of Faculty re asking Cole to write recommendation for John T. Dunlop; Harvard University re alumni information; Paul M. Herzog, National Labor Relations Board (NLRB) Chairman and later Associate Dean, Harvard Graduate School re personal; with Carl Holderman, New Jersey State CIO Council, re Senator Sparkman's voting record against the original Taft-Hartley Act; John Hope, Specialist on Industrial Relations, Fisk University re requesting information on the subject of racial discrimination by the non-operating railroad union and Cole's reply; Senator and Vice-President Hubert Humphrey re Cole's participation as a member of the National Citizen's Committee on International Cooperation and routine; other routine and personal..
- Inland Steel Co., 1964-1976 (Box 3, Folder 1115)
  Correspondence with company and union officials re arbitration/mediation on cases - concerning scheduling arbitration hearing dates, appeals, bills for services, memos, form letters..
- I, 1951-1954 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Irving Ives (Senator) re his (Ives) appointment as President of the 36th International Labor Office Conference; other routine and personal.
- J, 1944-1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Lyndon B. Johnson, President, letter requesting Secretary Wirtz and Secretary Hodges to get up meeting of the Advisory Committee on Labor-Management Policy with Cole, appointing Cole Chairman of the Emergency Board; expressing gratitude for Coles's work on Presidential Advisory Committee on Labor-Management Policy and accepting his resignation; letter expressing gratitude for Cole's work in connection with Missile Sites Labor Commission and letter appointing Cole as special mediator in the East and Gulf Coast Longshore dispute; and other routine.
- J, 1952-1953 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Joint Council on Economic Education. Routine.
- K, 1944-1963 (Box 4, Folder 3-6)
  John F. Kennedy, President - letter appointing Cole member of Emergency Board - Pan American and Transport Workers Union (TWU), letter thanking Cole for his work as Chairman of Board of Inquiry in the maritime industry labor dispute, letter terminating the Board of Inquiry and thanking Cole again; letter from Kennedy (Senator) re thanking Cole for his willingness to serve on a panel to advise the Committee with respect to amendments to the National Labor Relations Act (NLRA) and setting up an organizational meeting, letter thanking him for serving; letter from Robert Kennedy, Attorney General re meeting at White House which Cole attended concerning lawyers and affirmative action; Clark Kerr, routine; Theodore W. Kheel re personal and routine; with Leo Kotin, arbitrator, re various arbitration cases; other routine and personal.
- L, 1944-1964 (Box 4, Folder 7-9)
  William M. Leiserson, routine; John L. Lewis, President, United Mine Workers (UMW) - letter informing Cole he cannot attend session at NYSSILR, letter thanking Cole for his kind words upon Lewis' retirement; other routine and personal.
- M, 1944-1955 (Box 4, Folder 10-14)
  Lois MacDonald, New York University re labor relations in the milk industry; with Professor Jean McKelvey, Cornell University, re Cole's teaching at Cornell and other mutual interests - arbitration, AFL-CIO umpire ship; Whitley C. McCoy, Director, FMCS; with John McGinley, of McGinley Mills, Inc. re his employees wishing to withdraw from union; with U.S. Department of Labor Secretary James P. Mitchell re Mitchell's participation in a labor conference at Cornell University, thanking Cole for his work as Chairman of Advisory Committee on Labor-Management Relations in Atomic Energy; with Edward R. Murrow, CBS, personal; other routine and personal.
- National Conference of Christians and Jews, Inc., 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 15)